Guide to the Aaron Vanderpoel papers, 1770-1866
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
Aaron Vanderpoel papers
1770-1866
3148
MssCol 3148
Vanderpoel, Aaron, 1799-1870
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
1.5 linear feet (4 boxes, 2 oversize folders)
Aaron Vanderpoel (1799-1870) was a lawyer, later a judge, in Kinderhook, Columbia County, New York, and in New York City. He was administrator of the estate of William Temple Franklin (1760-1823), the grandson of Benjamin Franklin. Collection consists of correspondence, legal papers, and financial documents of Vanderpoel and his father-in-law, attorney James McBride. Vanderpoel's papers pertain to his legal practice, judgeship and personal life. Bulk of his legal papers concerns his administration of the William Temple Franklin estate, 1770-1834. James McBride papers reflect his legal and real estate activities including his work on behalf of clients living in Ireland who had legal or real estate interests in New York City. Also, materials concerning land transactions in western New York and legal affairs of his clients.
Aaron Vanderpoel, 1799-1870 (or 1871) was a lawyer, later a judge, in Kinderhook, Columbia County, New York, and New York City, where he lived on East. Sixteenth Street near Irving Place. Vanderpoel was the administrator of the estate of William Temple Franklin, 1760-1823. Temple Franklin was the grandson of Benjamin Franklin, and the son of William Franklin, 1731-1813, the last royal governor of New Jersey. He served as Benjamin Franklin's secretary in Paris for eight years, beginning in 1776, and later edited his grandfather's papers. Temple Franklin married Hannah Collier (or Collyer), an Englishwoman, in Paris a few days before his death.
Vanderpoel's papers document his legal practice, his judgeship, and, to a lesser extent, his personal life. A group of legal papers, most of which appear to have belonged to his father-in-law, James McBride, is also included.
Papers documenting Vanderpoel's administration of the William Temple Franklin estate make up the bulk of his legal papers. The Franklin estate papers, 1770-1834, consist of correspondence (some arranged in an alphabetical file, the rest included among the legal and financial documents), legal and financial documents, copies of and extracts from the wills of Benjamin Franklin and Governor William Franklin, and maps. A small amount of this material is in French, and letters written by Hannah Collier Franklin, Governor William Franklin, and William Temple Franklin, are included. Topics covered include: claims of Hannah Collier Franklin and other heirs; lands owned by the Franklin family in New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Georgia, New York, and Indiana; legal affairs of Governor Franklin, particularly a debt owed him by Col. George Croghan; and Vanderpoel's termination of his role as administrator in 1866.
Also included are drafts or copies of Vanderpoel's letters, 1824-1845, concerning his legal practice (some additional Franklin matters are discussed here); legal opinions he issued while a judge, 1844, 1848, and undated; financial papers, 1824-1858; and a "cistpool" permit, 1844, for his Sixteenth Street house.
James McBride, Vanderpoel's father-in-law, was also an attorney. He represented clients living in Ireland who had legal or real estate interests in New York City. McBride also appears to have had real estate interests himself. A group of files arranged alphabetically by client name containing correspondence and legal documents, 1811-1848, largely reflects McBride's legal and real estate activities. Included is an undated map showing land in Greenwich Village owned by Aaron Burr (the connection to McBride, if any, is not apparent); significant amounts of papers concerning the estates of Terence Connolly and John Flack, and smaller amounts concerning the legal affairs of other clients (see the container list for a complete listing); and correspondence and legal and financial documents, 1835-1847, concerning transactions of land in Allegany, Cattaraugus, Genesee, and Wyoming counties in New York State, between McBride (with others) and the Holland Land Company.
1899, 1901, Received from Mrs. E. N. Vanderpoel
A small collection of papers, 1791-1886, of the Vanderpoel family of Kinderhook, including Aaron Vanderpoel, is at the Columbia County Historical Society; Kinderhook, New York.
Connolly, Terry; Flack, John; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Franklin, Hannah Collier; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823; Franklin, William, 1731-1813; McBride, James; Vanderpoel, Aaron, 1799-1870; Franklin family; Holland Land Company; Irish -- New York (State) -- New York; Law -- New York (State); Real property -- New York (State); Maps; Judges; Lawyers
- Legal and personal papers, 1824-1858
  - Letters, 1824-1845 (Box 1)
  - Financial documents, 1825-1858 (Box 1)
  - "cistpool" permit, 1844 (Box 1)
  - Legal opinions, 1844; 1848; undated (Box 1)
- William Temple Franklin estate papers, 1770-1866
  - Correspondence, 1791-1855
    - A-K (Box 1)
    - L-W (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, leqal and financial papers, 1770-1866
    - American affairs, 1770-1811 (Box 2)
    - Debt of Col. Croghan, 1771-1813 (Box 2)
    - 1785-1826 (Box 2)
    - Georgia lands, 1786-1796 (Box 2)
    - Copy of Benjamin Franklin's will, July 17, 1788 (Box 2)
    - Land papers, 1788-1826, undated (Box 3)
    - Extract from Gov. William Franklin's will, 1814 (Box 3)
    - Hannah Collier Franklin, 1827-1834 (Box 3)
    - Vanderpoel's discharge as administrator, 1866 (Box 3)
- James McBride leqal papers, 1811-1848
  - Aaron Burr (Box 3)
    (undated map of his property in Greenwich Village).
  - Terence Connolly, (See oversized box V) (Box 3)
  - Sarah Duncan and Samuel Boyd (Box 3)
  - John Flack (Box 3)
  - Charles French (Box 4)
  - John G. Glover (Box 4)
  - Holland Land Company (Box 4)
  - Thomas Atherton Howard (Box 4)
  - Barnard Keenan (Box 4)
  - John Kelly, (See oversized box V) (Box 4)
  - Peter McLaughlin, (See oversized box V) (Box 4)
  - James Twigg (Box 4)
- Additional Franklin legal papers and maps (Oversize box 5)
- Additional James McBride legal papers
  - Terence Connolly, (See box 3) (Oversize box 5)
  - Maria Cushman - a painting of a flower done by Cushman at Litchfield before her marriage, May 1814 (Oversize box 5)
  - Daniel Ewen (Oversize box 5)
  - John Kelly, (See box 4) (Oversize box 5)
  - Peter McLaughlin, (See box 4) (Oversize box 5)
  - James Newman (Oversize box 5)
  - Nicholas Prendergast and Winifred Bulger Prendergast (Oversize box 5)
  - James Whitley (Oversize box 5)